Guide to the Daniel Coit Gilman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Daniel Coit Gilman papers
1845-1910
MS 582
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, lectures, and other papers of Daniel Coit Gilman, educator, university president, and author. Included are papers regarding Gilman's career at Yale, the University of California, and Johns Hopkins University. Important correspondents include Charles M. Andrews, James Dwight Dana, William Henry Brewer, Timothy Dwight, Benjamin Silliman, Theodore Dwight Woolsey, and Andrew Dickson White.
Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth L. Anderson in 1943.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Special Files.
Scope and Contents
The Daniel Coit Gilman Collection is divided into three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Special Files.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter; letters written by Gilman are filed under the name of the person to whom they are addressed. Among the notable correspondents are: Charles M. Andrews, James Dwight Dana, William Henry Brewer, Timothy Dwight, Benjamin Silliman, Elisha Mulford, Moses Coit Tyler, Theodore Dwight Woolsey, Justin Smith Morrill, Josiah Gibbs, and Andrew Dickson White. Of special interest are those letters he wrote, mostly to his sister, Maria P. (Mollie) Gilman, during his travels in Europe from 1853 to 1855. In addition, there are a number of letters addressed to Gilman as the representative from Connecticut to the Universal Exposition at Paris in 1855.
SERIES II, WRITINGS contains both manuscript and printed articles, notes, and addresses pertaining to industrial, agricultural, and general themes in education, as well as materials relating to the history of higher education, both European and American. Of special interest is a series of lectures he gave at the University of California at Berkeley in 1883. There are also a number of biographical sketches of philosophers and scientists, and some material relating to Gilman's activities in behalf of the Yale Library and the Sheffield Scientific School.
SERIES III, SPECIAL FILES contains both manuscript and printed materials pertaining to the Sheffield Scientific School, the Winchester Observatory, the Yale Corporation, as well as newspaper articles written by Gilman as a means of defraying a part of his expenses during his European excursion of 1854-1855.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel Coit Gilman, educator, university president, and author, was born in Norwich, Connecticut, July 6, 1831, the son of William Charles and Elizabeth Coit Gilman, descendants of the founders of Norwich. He was educated at Norwich Academy where Timothy Dwight was a classmate. At the age of fourteen Gilman's family moved to New York City where he attended a school under the direction of Calvin Tracy, his old instructor at Norwich Academy. As a result of his excellent penmanship, Gilman was introduced to library work, obtaining a position with Henry Stevens to catalog the books from the library of George Washington which had been purchased in 1848 by the Boston Athenaeum. This was followed by catalog work in the Mercantile Library of New York, with S. Hastings Grant, whose intimate friend Gilman became. From this relationship grew Norton's Literary Gazette, which they edited for several years. Through their efforts there was held the first annual meeting of American librarians in 1853.
Gilman continued his studies at the Cornelius Institute in New York before entering Yale College in 1848. After graduation in 1852, he studied for a few months at Harvard College, living in the home of Professor Arnold Guyot, who aroused in Gilman an interest in geography. In December, 1853, he and Andrew Dickson White, a close friend and classmate at Yale, sailed for Europe as attachés of the American legation at St. Petersburg. After two years abroad, Gilman returned to the United States to become assistant librarian at Yale College. In 1858 he succeeded Edward C. Herrick as librarian. Gilman was also instrumental in founding the Sheffield Scientific School, in which he served for nearly seventeen years as librarian, secretary, and professor of physical and political geography. He was also a member of the New Haven Board of Education and was influential in the adoption by New Haven schools of graded classes.
In 1872 Gilman became president of the University of California, but left that post in 1875 to become president of the newly created Johns Hopkins University. He served as president of Johns Hopkins until 1902, during which period its mode of graduate studies became the model for American universities. Gilman's success was attributable in part to his ability to attract outstanding scholars to Hopkins, but also because he placed great emphasis upon science at a time when most American college presidents regarded science as inimical to the religious and moral development of their students. In addition, Gilman was largely responsible for making Johns Hopkins the leading center of medical education in the country.
Upon retirement from Hopkins, Gilman became the first president of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, D.C. In addition, he served as vice-president of the American Bible Society; was a member of the U.S. commission investigating the U.S.-Venezuela boundary dispute; served in 1879 as president of the American Social Science Association; was a trustee of various foundations, including the Russell Sage Foundation, the Peabody Education Fund, and the John F. Slater Fund; and served as president of the National Civil Service Reform League from 1901 to 1907.
Gilman was twice married: first, on December 4, 1861, to Mary Ketcham of New York City, who died in 1869, and again, on June 13, 1877, to Elizabeth Dwight Woolsey, who survived him by fourteen months, dying in 1910. Gilman died on October 13, 1908.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Clergy; Education; Geography; Libraries; Medicine; Science; Social sciences; Europe; New Haven (Conn.); United States -- Foreign relations; College presidents; Educators; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943; Brewer, William Henry, 1828-1910; Brush, George Jarvis, 1831-1912; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; DeForest, Henry S., 1833-1896; Durant, Henry, 1802-1875; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Fisher, George Park, 1827-1909; Gibbs, Josiah W. (Josiah Willard), 1790-1861; Gildersleeve, Basil L. (Basil Lanneau), 1831-1924; Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908; Gilman, Edward Whitney; Gilman, Elizabeth Coit, 1796-1868; Gilman, Emily Serena, 1835-1910; Gilman, Julia Silliman, 1826-1892; Lane, Louisa Gilman, 1838-1922; Gilman, Maria Perit, 1824-1906; Gilman, William C. (William Charles), 1795-1863; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Jewell, Marshall, 1825-1883; Morrill, Justin S. (Justin Smith), 1810-1898; Mulford, Elisha, 1833-1885; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Schouler, James, 1839-1920; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1815-1886; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Woolsey, Theodore Salisbury, 1852-1929; Johns Hopkins University; University of California, Berkeley; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- History; Yale University. Library
- Correspondence, 1845-(1854-1856)-1907; Series I; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into two sections: "General Correspondence" and "Family Correspondence." "General Correspondence" is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter; letters written by Gilman are filed under the name of the person to whom they were addressed. The letters within each folder are arranged chronologically with the exception of the Yale Bi-centennial folder which is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter. Among the notable correspondents not previously mentioned are: Noah Porter, Thomas A. Thatcher, George P. Fisher, Edward C. Herrick, Marshall Jewell, George Jarvis Brush, Basil L. Gildersleeve, Henry S. De Forest, James Schouler, and Theodore Salisbury Woolsey.
  "Family Correspondence" is also arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter; letters written by Gilman are filed under the name of the person to whom they were addressed. The letters within each folder are chronologically arranged. The correspondence with his brother, Rev. Edward Whiting Gilman, and his sister, Maria P. Gilman, is particularly important.
  - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, W. F., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Bible Society (copy), 1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Andrews, Charles McLean, [1896] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andrews, William W., 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "B" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baud, R., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baxter, David, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beardsley, Edward E., 1873 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Belcher, Nathan, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biddle, James S., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bopange, Hector, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bourjoin, F., (1854-1855?) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bowers, D. E., 1889 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brewer, William H., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bring, B. E., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bromberg, Samuel, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brown, T. S., 1854, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brush, George Jarvis, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Buckingham, William Alfred, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bureau of Education, Dept. of Interior, 1871-1878 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Busque, E., (1855?) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carroll, Charles, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Caswell, Alexis, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cattley, C. R., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chandler, Walter G., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chase, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - de Chermont, W., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clark, Edward P., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clarke, John L., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clayton, Henry, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Coligny, Charles, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Committee of Arrangements, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Re: Cook, Albert Stanburrough (Box 1, Folder 33a)
  - Cortelyou, George B., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Craig, J. E., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dana, James Dwight, 1852, 1854-1857, 1859-1860, 1862, 1873, 1876, 1884, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Darvill, Henry, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - DeForest, Henry Swift, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Dennison, Frederic, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Durant, H., 1872 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dwight, Timothy, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Easton Ledger [Md.], Haddaway G. E. (ed.), 1898 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Ecclesiastical Congregational Society, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Edwards, Edward, 1853, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Eichler, G., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Elliott, Colonel, Circa 1854 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Elliott, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Field, Maunsell B., 1854, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Fisher, George Park, 1900, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Flugel, J. G., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Foster, McNeve, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Foster, Verne, 1853, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Foster, William Edward, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Friedlander, Julius, 1854, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Friedrich, Johann N., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Fry, Henry I., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Funk, Ludwig, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Furness, Horace Howard, 1899, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Gardner, David Mason, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Gaulhiac, P. E., undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Gavelot, Jr., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gellespie, William M., Circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Gellibrand, Mary T., undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Gibbs, Josiah, 1879, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Gildersleeve, Basil Lanneau, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Grand Vien, F., 1854, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "H" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Harris, Jack, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Harvey, G., (1854-1855?) (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Hastings, Grant S., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Henry, Alex, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Herrick, Edward C., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Horner, B. S., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Howland, Joseph, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Hubney, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Huntington, E. B., 1859 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Hurlbut, George, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hutton, William R., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Invitations, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Invitations, Yale Alumni Association, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Jewell, Marshall, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - "K" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Kendrick, Green, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 82a)
  - Kingsbury, J. J., 1859 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Kirkpatrick, Charles, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Korff, M. Baron, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Kuler, James E., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Leavitt, Emily Wilder, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Lewis, Charlton L., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Libbey, William, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Library, Yale University, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Little, A. W., (1854-1855?) (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Lockwood, Radcliffe B., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - "M" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Maercker (Weber), A., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Maerker, F. A., undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Melber, E., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Merfit, H. M., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Merrill, Frederick J. H., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Moller, A. F., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Morrill, Justin Smith, 1858, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Mulford, Elisha, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Murray, David, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - "N" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Newton, H. A., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - North, E. D., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - "O" Misc., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Ostrow, Wassilli, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - "P" Misc. (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Pertz, Leonard, 1854, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Philip, Wm. H., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Pornoy, Alfred, undated (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Porter, Isaac Gleason (copy), 1863 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Porter, Noah, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Prochoroff, Alexander, 1854/1855 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Reid, William Thomas (Box 1, Folder 115)
    General
    See: box 1, folder 33a
  - Roberts, T. T., 1903 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Robinet, Edward, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Roche, L., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Ropes, F. L., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Ropes, Wm. H., 1854, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Ruggles, Samuel B., 1864 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Ruppel, Heinerich, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Russell, William H., 1853 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - "S" Misc., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Schouler, James, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Shaftesbury, Lord, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Sheperd, Charles, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Silliman, Benjamin, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Skinner, A. N., 1852 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Smiles, R. W., 1854 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Stadthagen, D., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Sterry - zunt, T., undated (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Swaine, J., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Teichman, L., (1855?) (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Tyler, Moses Coit, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Thatcher, Thomas Anthony, 1864, 1865, 1869, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Uhler, P. R., 1898 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Valentine, undated (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Vattemore, Alexander, 1854-1855 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Verkins, L. W., 1859 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Vierreck, H., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - Ware, William R., 1854 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Warne, Joseph, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Warren, Minton (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Weld, Mason C., 1854, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Wells, J. E., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Welsh, W. U., (1855?) (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - Whinney, William, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 147)
  - White, Andrew Dickson, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - Wilson, John, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - Wimmer, Herrmann, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 150)
  - Wisconsin, University of; N. B. VanSlyke, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Wood, Charles, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - Woods, I. C.; Wood Preserving and Steam Seasoning Works, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 153)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1865, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 154)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Salisbury, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 155)
  - Yale Bi-centennial, 1901 Oct, Nov, December (Box 2, Folder 156)
  - Young, Mason, 1872, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 157)
  - Unidentified, 1853, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 158)
  - Family
    - Circular letter to relatives and friends, undated (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Gillman, Alexander, 1892-1896 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - Gillman, Annie, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 161)
    - Gilman, Arthur, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 162)
    - Gilman, Caroline, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - Gilman, Caroline T., 1879, 1882, 1900-1902 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - Gilman, Edward Whiting, 1846, 1850, 1852-1853, 1855-1863, 1865, 1867-1870, 1878-1879, 1882, 1884-1885, 1891-1893, 1896, 1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 165-168)
    - Gilman, Elizabeth Coit, 1845, 1847-1855, 1857, 1861, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - Gilman, Emily, 1850-1853, 1855-1857, 1860, 1862-1863, 1870, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - Gilman, Hattie, 1848, 1854, 1857-1858, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - Gilman, Julia Silliman (mother), 1850, 1854, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 172)
    - Gilman, Julia S. (Bristol) (daughter), 1891, 1895, 1903, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - Gilman, Lawrence, 1904, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 174)
    - Gilman, Louise, 1845-1846, 1848-1850, 1853-1856, 1860, 1864, 1889-1890 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - Gilman, Marion P., (1845-1860) - 1904 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - Gilman, Sisters, 1846, 1889, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - Gilman, William Charles, 1848-1857 (Box 3, Folder 178)
    - Gilman, William, Jr., 1850, 1852, 1854, 1862, 1868, 1902-1903 (Box 3, Folder 179)
    - Kingsley, James Luce, 1851, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - Kingsley, James Luce, Jr., undated (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - Perit, Maria Coit, 1859, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 182)
    - Thompson, Elizabeth Gilman, 1855, 1870, 1880, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 183)
    - Thompson, Joseph P., 1862-1864, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 184)
- Writings, 1850-1905; Series II; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series II, WRITINGS, is arranged chronologically and includes both manuscript and printed copies of articles, addresses, and notes.
  - Misc. notes re: Yale, [1850, 1851?] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Dr. William Osler," "A Storm on the White Mountain" (newspaper articles), [1853] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes and drafts re: Yale Library, 1862-1865 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notes on the resignation of a Yale librarian, 1865 January 19 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Records of "Norton's Cadets," and notes and correspondence Yale men who served in the Civil War, for ceremony at Yale, 1861, 1865-1866 (Box 4, Folder 4a)
  - An Act Constituting a Board of Education, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Address before New Haven Colony Historical Society commemorating the removal of Yale College to New Haven in 1717, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notes on New England, 1867-1868 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Address on Foreign Experiences with Technical Education, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Galley fragment of article on Agricultural Schools at the University of California, [1874] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Industrial Education Lectures, San Francisco, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Address before California State Legislature: "The University of California, Its Scope, Success, Perils, Needs and Benefits,", [1874] (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes for addresses re: science and religion, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Address to U.S. Naval Academy, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notes for address on general education before public school teachers, Baltimore, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Notes for lecture on Newton, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Introduction to book on the writings of Francis Lieber (galley proofs) (edited by D.C. Gilman), 1879 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Tribute to Prof. Thomas Chalmers Murray, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Notes re: Leibnitz and, Malebranche, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Address before American Social Science Association, Saratoga, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Notes re: the Transit of Venus, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Addresses, Berkeley University Series, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Notes from a sketch of the life of John Slater, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Lecture notes on Tolstoi, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Address before Y.M.C.A. at Johns Hopkins, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Notes re: Frederick Denison Maurice, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Address before Worcester Industrial Institute: "Hand-Craft and Rede-Craft, A Plea for the First-Named,", 1885 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Article on Harvard University, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Address before graduates in Education course: "What is An Intellectual Life,", 1886 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Address on University Education, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Remarks on Florence Nightingale, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Address at the Brooklyn Institute on James Dwight Dana, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notes on a Ghost Story, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Address on George Peabody, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Address on Jonathan Trumbull, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Announcement on opening a medical school at Johns Hopkins University, [1893] (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - "The Sheffield Scientific School - A Semi-Centennial Historical Discourse,", 1897 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Remarks on Mendelssohn, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - "Fighters and Writers,", 1899 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Reviews of Gilman's "The Life of Professor James Dwight Dana,", 1900 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Tribute to Rev. Maltbie Babcock, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - "Centennial of the British and Foreign Bible Society,", 1904 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - "Cornerstone of the New Maryland Institute,", 1905 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Mss draft of Chapter 1, The Life of Daniel Coit Gilman by Fabian Franklin (written by W.C. Gilman), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Corrected Drafts of Chapter 1, The Life of Daniel Coit Gilman by Fabian Franklin (written by W.C. Gilman), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Final draft of Chapter 1, The Life of Daniel Coit Gilman, by Fabian Franklin (written by W.C. Gilman), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Notes re: European Educational Institutions, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Notes on the history of universities, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Remarks on the unveiling of the Statue of General Howard, Peabody Institute Baltimore, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Address before alumni of Johns Hopkins, "Inside View of University Work,", undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Misc. Lecture Notes for Medical College, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "Noble Uses of a Navy" (graduation day at Annapolis), undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Address before public school teachers; Baltimore, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Misc. Notes and Fragments, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - List of Addresses and Articles, 1856-1872 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Itinerary for lectures, 1871-1903 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Special Files, 1850-1910; Series III; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  SPECIAL FILES are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "An Act" relating to Yale College (Yale Fellows), 1872 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Articles from Europe, newspaper clippings, 1854-1856 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Carnegie Institute, Biographical Material, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "The Coffin Manor," geneological Mss copy, author unknown, and fragments, 1878 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Defense of the professors at Yale (a letter to the editor), 1869 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Finances, 1848, 1852 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Instructions for disposition of letters, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Johns Hopkins University. Biographical Material, 1876-1902 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Linonian Centennial, list of names, 1853 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - The Maker of Johns Hopkins, Reviews ( The Life of Daniel Coit Gilman by Fabian Franklin), 1910 (Box 6, Folder 10)